This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[music]
Hello and welcome listeners to Software
Engineering Radio. I'm your host Amey
Embodhi and today I'm joined by Eric
Shaffer.
Eric is the chief architect at Imply and
one of the original authors of the open
source Apache Druid project with deep
experience working on Druid across
engineering and leadership roles at
Splunk and Yahoo as well.
He previously served as VP of
engineering at Metamarkets where Druid
originated and was also a founding team
member of the diabetes data nonprofit
Tidepool. Today we will talk to Eric
about the world of observability
technology. Welcome to the show Eric.
It's great to have you here. It's great
to be here. Thanks for having me. Of
course. So, for listeners who may be
less familiar with the subject, how
would you define observability?
Observability, that's a great question.
I mean, you can start with just the
English word observe and that's looking
at things. But really as the internet
technology has evolved, as more services
have been given to people through
servers and technology, there's become a
need to understand how the systems are
operating, understand what's going on
inside of them and really be able to use
that to debug what happens when things
go wrong because things will inevitably
go wrong, right? And that notion of
being able to observe, understand what's
going on in the system and then actually
take action on the system as a whole, I
would bundle up all together into
observability. So, I think of
specifically observability in terms of
logs and metrics and traces. Is that all
or am I not covering something?
Oh yeah, absolutely. Like when you take
it down to fundamental data level, the
tools that people are using, the data
that people are using to observe is
logs, all those things we write in our
code that get dumped out to see, metrics
which give you a much broader view, you
can aggregate them, you can see across a
much wider view of what's going on
before you actually like drill down into
an issue, and traces of course where
especially with the advent and expansion
of microservices and service
orientation, being able to trace a
request as it's running through your
infrastructures very important. The one
thing I would add to it is the alerting
infrastructure because there's
definitely a need to respond to this
data, alert and bring people in. And
then I think most recently also agentic
and AI and all of that is coming into
the picture and that's one of those
things that I feel like the industry as
a whole is figuring out where it fits
and how it fits. Absolutely. So, right
now we see a lot of shift toward a
microservices based framework. Would you
say that observability is becoming
increasingly critical in systems like
that and how so? Yes, absolutely.
There's a fun meme about how to draw an
owl. I'm not sure how many of your
listeners are familiar with it, but it
starts with a picture of two circles and
then it goes to draw the effing owl and
it's like a fully fleshed out owl with
all the details and all of that. And
some people liken I've seen that meme
used to respond to Kubernetes where it's
like, here's how to do something in
Kubernetes, deploy hello world app, now
deploy everything else. And it's a big
jump, but with microservices, with
things like Kubernetes, there's a lot
more kind of independent moving pieces
and there's good reason to have them. It
separates concerns, it gives you
independent access of scale so that you
can adjust your system to align with
what's actually happening. But along
with that comes a complexity of knowing
like, is it this part of the system or
is it that part of the system or is it
this service over here? And that's
really requiring a lot more stuff out of
the observability systems, out of what's
going on and where are things happening.
So, it brings me perfectly into talking
about the general idea here of tight
coupling and decoupling observability
frameworks. Of course, what you just
mentioned is absolutely true, that meme
of an owl, a lot of people can relate
especially with their work, right? But
when you think of the observability
stack at most places today, what does a
typical tightly coupled framework look
like? Can you describe it for me? Yeah,
so the tightly coupled observability
stacks really it comes back to people
start with well, I want to be able to
see this thing. I want to be able to see
my logs or whatever and they're like,
okay, well what's going to let me see
the logs? And then they get into what's
the data, where am I going to store it
and how am I going to interact with it
and stuff. And so in the logging space,
I feel like this notion of a tightly
coupled just log stack, Splunk was the
first one I ever interacted with. And
this was many years ago where you just
tail your logs, you throw them in Splunk
and you write some things and you find
stuff in the logs and it gives you an
aggregated source of logs. So, you have
logs from a whole bunch of different
services, a whole bunch of different
physical machines coming into one place
so that you can see them. And so, Splunk
is a tightly coupled thing. It has a UI
component that interacts with its
database layer and there's forwarder
agents that are used to push data in.
Over time that's evolved like
Elasticsearch has gone into that space
and there's this thing called the ELK
stack, the Elastic Logstash Kibana
stack. And so, Elastic, the open source
project, you can use Logstash to grab
your logs, you can push them into
Elastic, you can then use Kibana on top
of that in order to see the logs and
interact with it. Even in the Grafana
world, Grafana started as a UI for
interacting with metrics. But they've
also started building in logging
capabilities. They have this open source
thing called Loki DB which is a database
for logs and they've leaned in heavily
to this thing called OpenTelemetry which
is an open source kind of agent tree for
collecting logs, metrics and traces. But
I've mentioned Splunk, I've mentioned
the ELK stack, I've mentioned Grafana
and even like the ELK stack and Grafana,
they're open. They're open source,
they're wide open, but you always use
them in a stack. Each of these things is
always vertically integrated. You've got
your UI on top of your database on top
of your data acquisition. And even if
you go to the cloud vendors, you go to
Datadog, Datadog has a way you get data
and then they vertically integrate
everything in their nice walled gardens.
You go to Dynatrace, it's the same
thing. You go to New Relic, it's the
same thing. And really in this world,
everyone has kind of said, well, we're
going to get the data from somewhere,
but then we're going to put it in our
database and we're going to build our UI
against our database and that's going to
be a thing. And that's really the
vertically oriented stack that kind of
gets you stuck in a walled garden once
you put your data in there. I see. We
will talk more about some of these
examples that you shared, but I want to
talk more about the general
organizational structure of these
coupled stacks since they're stacked on
top of each other, where do you think
the pain shows up? Like what breaks
first at an organizational scale? Can
you share an example of where vendor
lock-in pain that you may have witnessed
because of this? Yeah, I mean, there's
lots of examples of where vendor lock-in
kind of comes in, but the most acute is
I mean, if you start from the beginning
and you start from nothing, it's pretty
easy to believe, oh, I'll just grab this
system, I'll put everything in there.
I'm going to have all my logs, all my
traces, all my metrics in this one
system. And as long as you only have one
product and one small group of teams or
one small group of people working on a
product, you'll probably stick with that
system because everyone has learned it,
they know how it works and they'll do
their things. But let's say your company
grows, it expands, some other team comes
in. That other team might be like, no,
we like this system. We want to use this
and we're going to use Loki DB with
Grafana and OpenTelemetry and another
team is like, we're going to use
Logstash with Kibana and Elastic. And
with the introduction of microservices,
you tend to have organizations
where a team owns a service
and that team is supposed to kind of
have some sort of autonomy about how
that service works. And a lot of times
that leads into these other knock-on
infrastructure choices of where do the
logs go and these other things. And so,
at especially larger enterprises, I feel
like there's generally a constant
struggle for a new team, a new product
line coming up wanting to be agile and
quick and adopt some brand new thing
while there being some standard that
there's some body of ivory tower type
people in the enterprise saying,
everybody must use this thing because
that consolidates all the things. And
then at especially large organizations,
there might be some acquisitions. They
might buy a company. That company knew
nothing about the ivory tower in your
enterprise. That company knew nothing
about your new product. They just made
decisions all on their own. And now you
end up with this sprawl where each
independent vertically or integrated
stack has some data in it. But when you
want to know what's going on across all
of them, it's hard. You can't figure it
out. You can't really look across them.
You're switching from one tool to the
other to the other. And then you've got
to take on these massive Okay, we
acquired you. Now you need to move all
of your log data into this system so
that we can actually bundle it into the
things that we're doing. And you get
into big movements like that. You get
into political battles with that brand
new product team who's like they're in
charge of doing this brand new thing
that everybody loves, but they're doing
it on some new infrastructure that's now
causing a bunch of consternation for
other people and political battles. And
that's one of the places where it really
really shows up as a strong pain point.
So, we will talk more about the solution
here being decoupling. But I want to
talk a little about the reasoning behind
this. It seems like from my
understanding the business intelligence
world is decoupled into these a
three-layer cake, if you think of
visualization, data infrastructure, and
then ETL. Yep. Why hasn't the
observability world followed the same
path till now? So, it's not actually a
why hasn't it followed it. It's just a
question of timeline. And this is also
something that we've noticed as a
company at Imply. We've had a number of
customers in the business intelligence
world and a number of customers in the
observability world. And really what I
think it is is that it's just the
business intelligence market has had
more time to evolve than observability
and security. Observability and security
are business intelligence 20-30 years
ago. And if we go back to where business
intelligence was, you're exactly right
to say that there's a three-layer cake
today. But you go back to where it
started with decision control systems.
These are the really old systems. You
might have heard of like Siebel systems
and some other things like that. Or SAP
kind of started back there. These are
systems that came around that were
starting to say, "Hey, we can collect
some data to help business people make
business decisions." And they were
called decision control systems. And
these started out as vertically
integrated stacks. Because at the time
the technology we didn't have databases.
We didn't have SQL at that time. We
didn't have those things. It was well,
someone wrote some code. They're storing
some data and now they're making it
visual. Then over evolution that
decoupled into a reporting layer on top
of databases. And that's when the
relational database started coming into
the world. That's when SQL really
started taking hold. You had like
Crystal Reports and a few things like
that enter into the market and drive
things. MicroStrategy is another company
that came in as a visualization layer.
But there was this separation
of the data layer from the visualization
layer. And that drove a lot of
innovation. And then people realized
that oh, now we need another set of
tools to help us get data into this data
layer. And that gave birth to ETL. And
really that came from the same thing
that I was just mentioning earlier in
terms of the pain of a walled garden,
the pain of a vertically integrated
stack. And the reason it evolved in
business intelligence is
that need to be able to take the data to
a lot of different places. If when you
acquire that company, you know their
data is going to be accessible via SQL,
it's so much easier to make sure that
the way you're interacting with the data
is going to be able to work with it.
It's so much easier to take those tools
and maybe you do want to migrate them
from this database to that database, but
you're not whole hog changing everything
soup to nuts. You're just changing one
little piece, moving stuff, and keeping
people's workflows intact. And so, the
business intelligence market evolved
very explicitly from tightly integrated
verticalized walled gardens into this
decoupled three-layer cake of the
visualization on the data platform on
the ETL and data acquisition. And I
mean, that is exactly where
observability and security are going as
well because that is the natural
evolution of a tightly coupled
verticalized stack. So, that's very
interesting. It makes me want to ask you
more questions about this layered model
and architecture of the decoupling. Mhm.
When we talk about decoupling the
observability layer, what are the
distinct layers that you see? What goes
through the architecture? Is there an
ingest layer, a data storage layer,
query compute layer, visualization
layer? Yes, I think it's the same layers
in business intelligence. My general
take on things is that history always
repeats itself. There's so many
different ways you can say it. Like
there's nothing new under the sun.
History always repeats itself. Like what
we see is the exact same pattern
repeating itself just with slight
variations. And so, absolutely the
business intelligence three-layer cake,
that is how it's going to decouple. We
already see it with OpenTelemetry.
OpenTelemetry is basically the
equivalent of the ETL layer. It's an
open-source way to get data into a
system. It can route to all sorts of
different systems. You can run one OTEL
collector. OTEL short for OpenTelemetry.
But you can run one OTEL collector and
have it route to all the different
places. Like that's already happening.
The thing that hasn't happened and is
really what is I believe going to be
happening or is happening is the
separation of the data layer from the
interaction layer and the UI. And how
did that happen in the business
intelligence world? SQL made it happen.
There was basically SQL fundamentally
became a de facto standard. There were
all sorts of different ways of querying
things back in the day, but SQL won.
Everything's on SQL and that's there.
Now, why hasn't it worked quite that way
in security and observability? It's
because
the data itself is slightly different.
And SQL is a very good language for when
you have highly regimented structure to
your data that you're interacting with
and working with. And it's a great
language for getting answers to
questions about well-structured data.
What we find in the security and
observability world is that people need
something that looks and feels a bit
more like programming. Less like just
I'm writing a declarative statement and
wanting to get something out. And more
like programming where they want to be
able to iterate, to change, to add
things and flow. And so, really in the
security and observability world,
there's a whole new chunk of query
languages. Splunk has SPL. Kibana uses
its own flavor of things based on some
JSON objects for querying things.
Grafana and Loki DB use this thing
called LogQL. In the Microsoft Azure
world, Sentinel and there's this
language called KQL, which was the Kusto
query language. CrowdStrike has CQL.
There's a whole bunch of different query
languages. And in the security and
observability space, these query
language, they're all pipe-based
operators. So, they look a little bit
more like your bash commands where you
have a command, you pipe the results
into another command, you pipe that into
another command. And it allows for kind
of more programming-style
interactions that it turns out those are
really useful and necessary in the
observability and security world. And
that's just logs. We get into metrics,
there's PromQL for querying metrics. And
that's a time series-oriented way to
query metrics. It started with
Prometheus and it's now pretty much a de
facto standard, I would say. On the
trace side of things, I think it feels
like there's not one query language
there. But really, so the answer to this
decoupling is the query language. And
the real thing that's different between
observability and security and business
intelligence is that there's not one
query language. There's multiple
different query languages.
But as a software engineer, as a
developer, as someone working in data, a
lot of people deep in like implementing
databases will try to convince you that
different query languages are not
actually different. They all condense
down to the same basic operations. It's
just different ways of representing it.
And that I think is the key fundamental
thing because that's actually true. But
there's not many systems that have
proven it out. There's not many systems
that take multiple different query
languages and execute all of them on the
same data.
I want to take an example here from the
BI world. Uh-huh. Let's say I have
Tableau or Grafana for visualization.
Mhm. Snowflake or SQL Server for the
data and Kafka or the ETL tools for
acquisition. Yep. If this is my stack,
similarly, how does that compare to this
BI world separation? In practice, where
do teams actually get stuck usually?
Okay. Yeah, so in practice. So, if we
take Tableau on top of Snowflake or
Databricks on top of DBT or Informatica,
Fivetran, something like that. Your DBT
Informatica, the ETL layer is your
OpenTelemetry. That's pretty standard
these days. The Tableau, if you're
dealing with Splunk, Tableau would be
Splunk UI. And then Snowflake would be
your Splunk indexers. If you're in
Elastic world, Tableau would be Kibana.
And Snowflake would be the Elasticsearch
cluster. If If in the Grafana world,
Tableau would be Grafana and Snowflake
would be Loki DB. If you're in DataDog
land or Dynatrace land or New Relic
land, you're just working with the UI.
So, all you see is the Tableau thing and
then behind the scenes, each of those
cloud vendors is running their own
version of the Snowflake. And that's
what they're seeing and those are the
things where people get stuck is as long
as they're staying in that walled
garden, they're not that stuck. They're
okay. The problem is it's hard to move
walled gardens. It's hard to change. And
so, as organizations expand, as
different people bring new ideas, it's
hard to evolve away from a specific
walled garden. The other challenge with
any of these walled gardens is when it's
hard to move away from it, there's no
economic incentive for the vendor who's
delivering you the walled garden to
maybe believe that you can pay more
because it costs a bunch to actually
move off. So, maybe you should give them
a little bit more money cuz either way
it's going to be more expensive to move.
So, why not? And so, there ends up being
an economic incentive or disincentive
around it. And also, as an organization
sprawls and expands, this is the real
source of siloed data where you actually
have data silos because they're stuck in
vertically integrated stacks.
I want to hit on your first point, which
is portability. We want to make
telemetry data interoperable,
which means we would now want to discuss
a little more about like schema and
evolution. How is schema evolution
across layers being handled? When the
ingest layer changes, for example, how
do you make the downstream layers adapt
if you're using different types of query
languages here? That's a great question.
And that's one of the things that I
actually find most interesting about the
difference between the business
intelligence data and very explicitly
logs. Logs don't have a schema. They do,
but they don't. There's repetition.
There's common repetition in logs. They
say the same thing over and over on
different log lines. And there's
information embedded in logs that you
can think of as fields. You could think
of as columns and you want to extract
them and do things with that. That's a
very common thing in logs. But there's
not really fundamentally a schema. It's
just whatever the developer wrote out as
their logs, that's the log line. And
you're getting at stuff. And you see
this with log-oriented query languages
and log-oriented experiences.
Really, all of them have some way of
allowing you to interact with the log
itself doing term searches where you're
just looking for strings inside of the
log. You don't have field names. You
don't know column names. You're just
saying, "Give me all of the logs that
have this word or this subset of
letters, this wildcard search type of a
thing." They all have some experience
that allows you to interact with the
data by just finding letters or finding
words in it. But then, they also have
this notion of, "Well, when the log line
looks like this, I want to extract these
things from it. And I want to think
about those things from an analytical
perspective." And so, as an example, you
might have a log line where someone's
saying, "I just dealt with an HTTP
request and it took me 20 seconds or 20
milliseconds or whatever and I returned
500 bytes." That plain text, that text
might be in the log line, but you might
want to pull out the 20 seconds or the
20 milliseconds as a latency measure.
You might want to pull out the number of
bytes as a byte measure. And now,
something like that, people tend to have
very normal structure around. But a
normal log line, there's a lot of times
that we will put variables into the log
line and it's nice to extract them out
and think of them as their own column
almost when interacting. And so, while
it's both schema-less,
people do they have assumptions of
schema on the data, but all of the
experiences, all of the query languages
actually have this as a common thread
where anything that's built around
dealing with logs has some way to just
find the line based on the characters
and another way to interact with these
fields that have been pulled out of it
in order to gain more value. And so, I
think the shift really is that the thing
to unify on is not can we figure out a
unified schema.
The thing to unify on is can we find the
commonalities in the actual language and
the actual way that people are querying
and support all of the different query
languages. And when you shift to that,
there's actually a lot more commonality
in how the query languages need to
operate than there is in the actual
shape of the data.
To make telemetry actually portable, we
would need some form of standardization,
don't you think? Like how would you
standardize the event or the log or the
metric or the trace schemas? Or do you
not do that at all? So, in my mind, the
standardization comes from the query
language. So, my belief is that
standards are almost always de facto
standards. The only standards that
actually ever exist are de facto
standards because people adopted them.
And then maybe the thing that everyone
adopted, a standards body got built
around and they evolved it and fixed
stuff because a de facto standard always
comes with some organic evolutionary
element to it because someone just
randomly dreamed it up because it's what
they needed and then everyone started
using it and then the cracks started
being seen. But anyway, so a de facto
standard takes shape. Everyone starts
using it. A standards body gets built
around that and then it goes. And that's
really where standards come from. And I
think the thing with the actual
structure and shape of data is that each
individual team, each new application,
each new thing is always necessarily
going to change the shape of the data.
But the thing that doesn't necessarily
change is the language that people want
to use to interact with the data. And
so, the real standard is not trying to
figure out how that data should be
shaped, but figuring out how that data
should be interfaced with. And that's
really the query language. And so, to
me, that's the actual key to the
standardization so that you can decouple
is supporting the query languages
because that's the thing like even as
all of these walled gardens, all of the
vertically integrated stacks, they have
some sort of query language. They have
some sort of query API between their
data layer and their visualization
layer. And the simple hand-wavy thing,
if you can support all of those APIs,
you can support all of those interaction
layers. And each of those APIs is
fundamentally a query language.
If you support all of those APIs, how
would you maintain things like context
like trace log correlation because that
kind of stuff is important for
debugging. Would that be a problem when
data is flowing through these multiple
systems? That's the thing here. The key
is not that the data's flowing through
multiple systems.
When you implement that query language,
when you implement that query API, all
of the data's residing in one place and
you have multiple different query APIs
on it. And so, you can think of traces.
Traces, you have spans which are
individual interactions and then they
combine together via trace ID to make a
whole chunk of interactions, right? You
can think of each of those spans as a
log. And then you can think of a trace
as the collection of all of the logs
that happened together, right? Now, if
you have those logs in the same system
that is implementing your trace queries,
you can now from a log-oriented query
language, you can interact with all of
those spans as logs. From a
trace-oriented query language, you can
interact with that group of logs as if
it was a trace. And so, from that one
place, by having the data in one place
and implementing different query
languages on it, each of those query
languages can basically put their
opinion, their assumptions of the data
on top of that data and allow you to
look at it from that lens. And so, the
underlying data itself is not actually
changing. It's the lens that the query
language puts on top of it that gives
you a different view.
Let's think of these observability tools
and these languages, PromQL, LogQL, SQL.
Can you walk me through how a trace ID
would flow from application code through
collection, storage, and into a
dashboard? Sure. So, OpenTelemetry
actually does define a general schema
for spans and traces and how that is.
And all of the spans will have a trace
ID field as JSON objects. But so,
they'll have a trace ID field and that
would be the same field that runs
through all of them. So, each of your
systems might generate a span. That
would all flow through an OpenTelemetry
collector or something like that, which
would then route it into your
observability, your data layer. So, you
would get multiple different spans from
multiple different systems all routed
into the data layer. Now, each of those
spans, they're JSON objects in the
OpenTelemetry world. So, each of those
spans is a JSON object. You can think of
a JSON object as a log line. You can
think of it as just some random text
that's a log line. And so, you might
have that in your data system and you
could use your SPL, you could use your
elastic query, you could use your log QL
to interact with each individual span as
if it was a log line. And so, if there's
a message on that span about what
happened in the system, you can see that
as a log, you can interact with it, you
can find it, and anybody or any
dashboard that is basically showing
activities that happened in logs, they
would see the spans in response to those
queries and it would show up dashboards
there. Now, on that exact same data,
there's a trace ID running through the
whole thing. So, from the log
experience, you could put the trace ID
into your filter and you could see all
of the logs that happened with that
trace. But, if you now switch to a
trace-oriented experience, it might
already know that all of those log lines
are combined and so, it's now asking you
a question, okay, for all of the traces,
what's the duration from the earliest to
the latest? And how many of them
happened and and and what occurred and
how many errors happened or or things
like that where in that trace
experience, usually it's taking multiple
of those logs, pulling out information
from a couple of them, maybe doing
subtraction of timestamps between them
to find duration or something, pulling
those out and then doing analysis over
the things that it pulled out. So, that
data can flow through open telemetry,
can flow through whatever. It doesn't
even have to all flow through the same
way that you get data. You could have
some come from logstash, some come from
open telemetry, some come from a Splunk
forwarder. As long as it has that same
trace ID, you can use that to correlate
the items when you're trying to look at
things from the lens of a trace.
You can also use that to find the
individual items when you're trying to
look at the lens through the lens of a
log. And you can also from those things
have metrics. You can pull metrics out
of that. You can generate metrics and
aggregate them up and flow those through
kind of metric-oriented system as well.
In an industry where demand for verified
skill has never been higher, prove you
have the foundation to deliver [music]
results with the IEEE Computer Society's
new software professional certification
for emerging professionals.
Give your career the head start it
deserves. Visit
computer.org/certification
today.
Do you see some sort of universal
observability schema that comes in here
where the industry would standardize
everything or is that a little too
wishy? I fundamentally do not believe
there will ever be a universal schema to
data because I see the shape of data
similar to like us as human beings where
each new human that's born is just a
little bit different from everybody
else. And yes, there's commonalities.
Yes, there's things that look similar,
but it all ends up being different. So,
I don't believe we will ever have one
universal schema. I do believe that
there will be generally agreed upon
commonalities.
And people will run with it, but just
the reality on the ground
is that all it takes is one developer
to use a field named X for some new
reason and now your schema's all
destroyed. It no longer means what it
used to mean. And that just happens so
often and so regularly. I think
believing that that can be achieved is a
fool's errand. It just can't be
achieved, so you should just assume it
can't be achieved and then figure out
how to deal with it. I want to pivot
into talking about query compute and the
separation in practice. Yeah. So, when
storage is decoupled from the query
engine and we don't care about what type
of query is happening, do indexing
strategies change here?
The interesting thing is the indexing
strategies really align with the query
languages you're looking to support. And
fundamentally, that's the difference.
The raw data doesn't change. You can
think of of an indexing strategy as a
lens that you've put on top of the data
to make it easier to jump into certain
parts of that data. It's a way that
you're viewing the data to optimize
things. And so, like, if you want to
actually do full text search
of data as a log line, you need to have
some sort of index that allows you to do
full text search.
You can also just brute force it. You
can just say, whatever, I'm just going
to brute force it and find things, but
there's a performance penalty for that.
If you always have to look through all
of the data in order to brute force a
search, eventually, you're going to pay
more in CPU than you would if you
indexed the data and had the structures
that allowed you to just jump right to
the right data. And so, the indexing
structures really align with the query
pattern.
And they align with the way in which you
want to interact with the data
more than aligning with the actual data
itself.
Does that make sense? It does make
sense. Speaking of performance
penalties, you mentioned this. Does
decoupling add any kind of overhead?
What are the latency versus throughput
tradeoffs for incident response
workflows, for example, when
milliseconds matter?
So, decoupling storage and compute
absolutely can add latency. And
fundamentally, there is
a cold start problem where if you don't
have the data to look at yet, the query
has to get the data. The system the the
physical machine that is running the
query has to get the data to actually
look at it. And so, there is a cold
start latency problem. You mentioned
kind of detections or what we've seen is
there's two general use cases that
people have over this data. And we
separate them into detections and
investigation. Now, detections are
always on, always running. They're
running on things just trying to see is
something bad happening? Is something
going wrong? Is Is there anything going
on? This tends to happen on the most
recent data. There's a very quick
drop-off where people are doing
detections on the most recent 5 minutes,
the most recent 15 minutes, the most
recent hour. Once you get 3 days old, 7
days old, you're not really doing active
detections on that data anymore. You
just have it there just in case or when
you want to come and do a longitudinal
analysis, when you want to look quarter
to date or the bigger thing is sometimes
those detections, and this definitely
happens in the security world, those
detections alert you to an intruder in
your network. They alert you to
something going on that's wrong and now
you have to figure out when it started.
And so now, maybe you know about this IP
address that is suspicious and you're
like, uh-oh, this
stuff bad was happening from this IP
address. What happened? And now you need
to go back
and you need to look and find all the
things that happened from that IP
address. And maybe in finding that, you
find new IP addresses. And now you're
like, okay, I need to expand the search
to include this one now. You find new
things and you're going back. And the
real thing about this is you don't know
how far back you're going to need to go.
You just kind of need to go back until
you're like, well, I've gone back far
enough and I'm not finding anything
anymore, so it must be done, right? And
you don't know what breadth of data you
need to look at. You don't know which
systems they eventually got into. You
don't know where they got. You don't
know what they did. And so, you're
really investigating the full set of
your data and everything that you're
needing to run with. And this separation
of use cases, in the detection case, you
absolutely do not want the cold start
problem. You want things to be always
on, you want them to be always running,
but you're also always querying and
interacting with the data. And so, it
makes sense to be spending CPU cycles on
that and have infrastructure that's
always running and doing things because
it is actually always running and you're
always doing stuff with it. But, for the
investigations, you're only going to
look at that data when you're doing the
investigation. You're only going to look
at that data at certain times. And so,
there's a notion of kind of ephemeral
compute or ephemeral storage. And the
public clouds really introduced this
quite widely, this notion of being able
to do things serverless, being able to
spin up CPUs just to do a thing and then
spin them down. And getting that into
the data world, getting that into the
security investigation world, I think
it's an important element and aspect of
things that decoupling storage and
compute really enables. And in that
world, yes, there's a cold start
problem, but that's fine because storing
the data, having the data accessible was
what you were trying to achieve. Having
that in S3 kept it cheap it kept it
economical, having it in cloud storage
and object store, whatever, kept it
economical. But, now you actually need
it. Now you actually need to query it.
And while you're querying it, you want
to do things fast. You want to do things
rapidly. You're going to iterate. It's
not just one query and then you're done.
You're going to do a query, then you're
going to do another query, then you're
going to do another query, and you're
going to keep iterating. And so, you
really want a high degree of flexibility
there where the cold start is not as big
of a deal, but you need to maintain
performance and speed across queries.
That's really where the rub comes in.
What about caching strategies? How do
they work in this decoupled
architecture? Where does caching
actually happen? The most common
approach, and I mean, well, it just
physically has to happen this way, but
the actual physical machine that is
running the CPU cycles for the query,
that's actually executing the query, has
to have some amount of the data cached
because CPUs they're interacting with
memory on the physical machine. That
memory is going to be populated either
by reading disk or reading something off
the network. When you're going to be
iteratively querying things, like if all
you ever need to do is query it once and
then you're done, you might as well just
read it off the network and throw it
away. There's no point in actually
caching stuff. But as I mentioned
earlier, you're going to query it once,
you'll find an IP address that you care
about. Now you're going to want to query
for that IP address. It's the same data,
but you're now looking for a new IP
address. You're looking for a new thing.
At that point you're doing multiple
iterative queries on the exact same data
and there you want the data on disk so
that it can then be loaded into memory
from disk rather than having to go back
out to the network, right? And so a very
common strategy is you have some
physical machines that when they get the
query, they have the data, they make it
available for query, they're querying
it. Then those machines go away and
public cloud makes this incredibly easy
to do. You can just spin up some EC2
instances, fill up their disks, throw
them away, move on with your life. And
so that's the most common high-level
idea of caching. It's infinitely deep
though because
the thing you actually need to respond
to a query,
like
maybe there's 100 megabytes of data and
you only need to look at 1 megabyte in
order to actually respond to that query.
And so you can get into a a really deep
amount of depth of trying to be like,
well, I don't want to download the whole
100 megabytes just to look at 1
megabyte. Is there any way I can figure
out that I only need this 1 megabyte and
only download that so that I can speed
up the cold start and then I keep that
cash and if I need another megabyte,
fine, I'll grab that when I need it.
That's kind of the the fundamental push
and pull of what it means to cash in
these decoupled architectures. Where
does Apache Druid come in? What role
does it play in this architecture? And
can you also pivot into talking a little
more about where Imply comes in? Yeah.
Yeah, so talking a bit about Imply and
Apache Druid. So real brief
introduction. Imply is a company we
started as a commercial entity around
the open source Apache Druid project.
Apache Druid's been doing distributed
OLAP oriented analytical processing
queries for a while. We've recently
introduced this product called Lumi,
which is a log oriented experience built
on top of Apache Druid. And so it is
Druid at the core with other things
around it. It's its own product and what
it's doing is it's leveraging Druid and
leveraging the internals of Druid, which
can do this kind of on the fly caching.
It can it can do distributed it it
handles queries across a distributed
cluster. It handles availability,
uptime, a whole bunch of operational
concerns that make it easy to just kind
of scale out and deal with stuff. We're
we're running in Apache Druid, but we've
added our own smarts. We've added our
own compression technology. We've added
log specific compression. We've added
log specific indexing on top of the log
specific compression. And we bundled all
of that up into Druid and we've
implemented multiple query languages on
top of that same data so that you can
pull that data in and you can now
interact with it for multiple different
ecosystems kind of all at the same time,
which is is really what I was talking
about earlier where this is
fundamentally decoupling the interaction
layer. It's it's decoupling the Splunk
UI, the Kibana, the Grafana from the
actual data layer itself and allowing a
user, allowing an admin to put data into
us and give that to whichever UI people
want to work with it. Even Tableau, even
Looker, even the SQL based ones.
I want to talk about the operation of
these pipelines end to end. What
collection and routing patterns work
best like OpenTelemetry collectors and
vendor agents and gateways do they fit
into this
pipeline?
Yes, in terms of our product, we support
OpenTelemetry
forwarders, Splunk forwarders, a heck
format, and a number of things like
that. One of the things we've seen
people ask for the most with this though
is we've seen a tendency in this world
where people are routing their data into
cloud object store. They've already got
the data flowing into S3. They've
already got it flowing into Google Cloud
Storage. They've already got it flowing
into Azure Blob Storage. They already
have the data flowing into some cloud
object store because it's cheap. It's a
known quantity. Their organization
works with it. They know how to get
there. There's a whole bunch of tooling
for just dumping data into those places.
And then they're like, well, I have it
here. Let me query that, please. And so
that's one of the interesting things
that I'm not quite sure exactly how it's
all going to play out. So OpenTelemetry
of course works. Your forwarders work,
all of that. But a lot of times people
are just dumping the stuff into a cloud
object store and then saying I'm going
to figure out how to query it after the
fact. And so that's also a very common
pipeline that honestly I think it makes
a ton of sense. It's like, oh yeah, I
totally get that because you know, if
it's in that object store and you can
interact with it, then you can take it
anywhere. It kind of breaks the vendor
lock-in to a certain degree, but we can
take it a step further. If we can make
that cloud data queryable by all of your
different interaction patterns, by all
of the different interaction layers, now
you can put it in the cloud, make it
available and have all your users
interact with it. That's the vision of
where we're going. That's what that's
what we're trying to enable is that the
unit economics, the cheap unit economics
of I'm just going to store it in the
cloud
combined with making that data available
with whatever interaction tool people
actually want to use.
Let's talk about this decoupled
architecture again. Mhm. When you think
of sampling for example, which is
critical decision, right, to determine
how to decide what you want and what you
want to drop. Yep. How do you avoid
losing high value signals like errors
and slow requests in a decoupled
architecture? There's a common challenge
with sampling and really this comes down
to anytime you choose to throw data
away,
you are making a choice today that you
will never need that data.
And if that's true,
if it's true that you really never need
that data, it was a great choice. It's
the most economical thing you can do
with that data if you never need it.
It's absolutely the best. The problem is
what happens when it turns out you did
need that data. What happens when it
when it turns out and so like one of the
things that happens especially with like
tracing is a user says they had an
experience. Developers go and look at
the traces and they're like, no, that
didn't happen. It doesn't show up in any
of the traces. And so that user's
experience is a micro experience. It's
one experience out of millions.
Maybe it gets caught in the sample,
maybe it doesn't. You have this happen
often enough and you have an end user
experience of this thing doesn't work
and you have developers saying, no, it's
always working. What are you talking
about? And eventually like you you can't
actually figure out the system. The
other thing is you can sample all you
want, but I think one of the thing
that's really happening in the industry
right now is with AI and with everything
that's going on, there's a lot more
government interest and regulatory
interest in what should happen with
data.
Where data should be, how long it should
be kept for and what should happen with
it. And as soon as it's a data set that
the government has regulated you must
keep for XYZ period of time, you can't
sample it away. You can't get rid of it.
And so really though sampling
fundamentally comes down to a question
of how do I improve the unit economics?
How do I improve the cost bottom line of
what I'm dealing with? It's really an
economic question more than it is an
actually meaningful technological
question. It's just an easy
technological answer to the cost
problem. There's other routes like
compression that you can also follow
that help to reduce unit cost
allowing you to store more without
actually throwing it away where you can
actually gain access to it. And so to me
I see sampling on one side and
compression on the other of a spectrum.
And absolutely, no matter how good your
compression is, if you 100% know you do
not need that data, throw it away,
please.
Great advice. What about the
observability of the observability
pipeline itself? How do you make sure
that your telemetry system is
Observability of the observability
pipeline. So as as a great question.
This always comes down to, you know,
it's turtles all the way down is is a
type of a thing. And so you you have the
observability watching the observability
watching the observability. And so I
mean, I can talk about for us what we do
is we have an internal system that
collects all of the data generated by
our production systems. And so we we use
our products to observe our product.
Then the question is where does that
product point its stuff to? And at some
point you have something that's pointing
its stuff to itself. For an end user,
for an end customer, hopefully you can
work with some vendor who's helping you
provide observability and then they're
the ones who are doing the recursive
thing where they're providing the
observability back into themself and you
get a production grade product that you
can work with, and you don't have to
worry about like that. That's the hope.
But, if you're doing things homegrown,
if you're if you're getting to that, at
some point, you're going to have a
system that you're generating stuff, and
you should put it into the same system
that you have.
But, that recursion, you're going to
have to come down to a point where
there's one system that's putting its
own observability stuff into itself.
Let's say I have a team that decided to
decouple the stack the way that you
recommended.
What are some common failure modes that
this team could
have [clears throat] that would showcase
that we didn't really decouple
correctly, or we did a poor job of it?
Failure modes for why the decoupling
didn't really work. I guess
I'm going to switch it to talk about
what what does it mean to be successful.
And if you didn't achieve success, then
it's a failure mode. Let's call it that.
And so, what does it mean to be
successful? And really, in my mind,
success is
you were able to put the data in one
place,
and you don't have to move that data,
but multiple different teams
can now interact with that data, and
they did not have to learn a new tool.
Whatever tool they have been
historically using, they're continuing
to use that, and they now have access to
more data. If that happened, it's been
successful.
If that hasn't happened, if putting the
data in that place now requires each of
these teams to learn a new tool, to
build a new workflow, to change what
they're doing, it's been unsuccessful.
So, would a decoupled architecture
actually cost more, or would it like
allow for easier control because it's
not costing as much? What is the cost
delta you're putting in?
be more cost effective because it should
allow for reducing duplication of
storage. It should allow for more
effective compression. It should allow
for more effective utilization of CPU
resources, of storage resources, of all
of that sort of stuff. And so, it
fundamentally should be more cost
effective.
What kind of governance problems could
potentially emerge if multiple query
tools are
querying the same data lake? Would there
be like access control issues? You
absolutely need to have access control
issues, or access control implemented.
You need to be able to control that.
Another element of it is sometimes
you want different teams to share the
same data, but you don't want them to
share the same physical CPUs. Because
sometimes your business analysts, their
query patterns are going to look very
different from your observability team,
from your security team.
And you can run into noisy neighbor type
situations where some query that looks
crazy to an observability or security
person, but makes tons of sense to a
business analyst, hogs all of the CPU
resources, and doesn't allow the
security or or observability
practitioner to do their job. And so,
it's much more common to want to have
the controls both around access control,
but also around infrastructure control,
to be able to
allow for different chunks of
infrastructure and compute and CPU to be
used for different use cases, so that
you can avoid people kind of stepping on
each other's toes in terms of getting
their job done. Let's say we have a team
that is very stubborn, and we force them
to work in a decoupled architecture, and
they still want to use multiple tools
with governance. They still want to use
Grafana alongside of everything that is
already implemented. Can they do it
safely and with governance? If the
decoupling is done right, yes. That's
kind of the definition of success. If
that team really wants to use Grafana,
they should be able to use Grafana, and
another team should be able to use
Splunk, and another team should be able
to use Kibana
without any issues between them. They
should all be able to see the same data,
and continue doing the workflow that
they want. And so, that that's that's
really the key of the decoupling, and
especially decoupling at the query
language, is that that stubborn team
shouldn't have to change their workflow.
That stubborn team should get to keep
their workflow. They just need more
access to data.
That suffices. I'll talk about the
tradeoffs, and maybe when is it not a
good idea to decouple? At what scale
does it not make sense to do this? What
would you say?
The only time when it could maybe not
make sense is actually at a small scale.
At the very very beginning, when you're
just like, I'm just setting some stuff
up, and I'm going to get some things in,
and I just want to be able to see stuff,
maybe at that point, like you just want
to pick something and run with it.
Simplicity in that case would be
helpful.
Right.
And so, if anything, it would be small
scale that would cause you to go with
the verticalized walled vendor, rather
than any sort of large scale. The
problems of kind of silos and
enterprises and big organizations and
different stubborn people wanting to use
different UIs, those become much more
painful the larger scale you get, rather
than the smaller scale. When you're a
team of three people, you can usually
work through that stubborn person who
really wants to use that one UI. For
team that is locked in with a specific
vendor the way that we talked about
before, what does a realistic migration
path look like? How do we talk about the
timeline, the team size, what they
learn?
If it's done right with what I defined
as success earlier, the migration path
basically becomes,
generally speaking, there'll be some
data set that isn't available in that
walled garden. That would be valuable to
have in in that garden. And so, the
migration starts with, well,
we can take this data set, we'll put it
in the decoupled world, and if it then
becomes available in the walled garden,
great. We've proven that we can add data
to this walled garden by putting it in
this decoupled thing. And you can go the
route of, okay, let's start dumping more
and more things in, because if you've
actually put it in there, and you
haven't impacted the end user workflow,
what what's to stop you? Why not? It
just becomes a migration of, okay, the
data's here, the data's there, but it's
still available via the same workflow,
so it's easy. And so, I'd say it starts
with
if you've got that data set
that you really want to make available,
but you're not doing it due to cost
restrictions, due to infrastructure, due
to what whatever,
you start with that. You proved yourself
that you can actually add something here
and not impact your end user's workflow,
and then from there, it just becomes a
question of what data you want to focus
on. Is it more important for you to gain
more access to more data sets that you
didn't have before, or is it more
important to take data sets that had
been locked in a system and unlock them?
And that can be done on a case-by-case
basis, really. And so, I'd say that
fundamentally, it can go as fast or as
slow as someone wants and what makes
sense for their organization.
So, that's a decision left to the team.
Mhm. What about for a team like this,
would they need to have a specific skill
set to operate in a decoupled
observability stack that they might not
have today? Maybe. It depends. As a
vendor in the space providing a product
in the space,
all you have to do is give us money, and
then you don't have to have the skill
set because we'll just operate it for
you. And then none of that's required.
If you're trying to go it alone, do it
yourself, then there might be some
stuff. You Understanding data systems,
understanding architecture,
understanding distributed systems and
stuff like that can become a bit of a
thing, but I mean, those are also all
skills that with the introduction of
microservices and the separation of
everything, I think people are
starting to become a little bit more and
more familiar with. And so, I don't
know. I'd say yes and no.
Mhm.
I'm going to wrap up here. I want to ask
you a couple more questions. If you
could give one piece of advice to
engineers evaluating whether or not to
decouple their observability stack, what
would it be? The one piece of advice is
yes, it should be decoupled.
[laughter]
It'd be think about what do you think
could become possible
if that data set that you're dealing
with, if that data set, if like you
could suddenly get a new data set and
and make it available to more teams.
Like what could become possible?
Thinking about that, I think, is an
interesting thought exercise. Think
about the future and what is ahead of
you. It absolutely has to be decoupled.
That's just naturally where things are
going to go. So, Eric, well, thank you
so much for your time today. Before we
wrap up, would you like to direct our
listeners on where to find you and more
about your work and your company?
I'm part of Imply. Website imply.io. Our
new product Lumi, as in like illuminate,
l u m i. Go to imply.io, read about
Lumi, look us up, try us out. Yeah, I'd
say that's the best way to connect and
see everything. And from there, you can
get to our socials, and you can get to
all of that stuff as well. Thanks so
much, Eric, for speaking with Software
Engineering Radio. Thank you for
listening. I'm your host, Ameya embody.
See you next time. Thank you.
[music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more [music]
about the podcast including other
episodes, visit our website at
SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
[music] through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
[music]
This and all other episodes of SE-Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
[music]
Thanks for listening.